[Music]
welcome to this session titled What's
new going open source with the new
GitHub repository for business Central
my name is Maria Jova and with me today
here is Alexander hrop Maria and I work
on the team that are working on taking
the business Central application open
source and this session here is going to
talk about how we did that for the
system application with the repository
called BC apps today's session we're
going to start out by talking who this
session is for and then we'll introduce
the bcfs repository we'll give an
overview of what's in there and then uh
we'll go over some of the automation
that we have set up in the bcfs
repository and finally we'll go through
an end-to-end process of how you as a
member of the BC Community can uh make a
contribution into the bcfs repository
from idea all the way to pull request
thank you Alex now let's get started
first let's cover who the session is for
first and foremost we are looking for
people with somewhat technical
experience in developing applications
for business Central we also want people
who are curious about how micros
Microsoft moves closer to collaborations
with partner we want people who are
willing to contribute source code to
unblock their own Solutions or they want
to uh they they're tired of uh doing
repetitive work and want to fix it once
and for all in the product itself now
let's uh take a look at a brief
introduction to BC apps it's a
repository hosted on GitHub uh and it
was actually launched officially in
November 2033 just before Direction s
since then we have built version 240 in
close in collaborations with the
community it has been forked a lot of
times we have nearly like 200 Stars a
lot of contributors nearly 400 merch PO
requests and 27 of these PO requests
were actually made by the community and
we're happy to announce that actually 21
made it with version 240 of the of
business Central with that we want to
express our gratitude and big thank you
for to all the
contributors uh now let's take a look at
the repository itself for the newcomers
for hopefully the new contributors that
we're going to have going forward this
is what you're going to see uh uh on the
front page when you go to AKs BC apps uh
I want to emphasize here that this
repository only hosts the source code
for applications developed by Microsoft
such as system application business
foundation and some of the developer
tools uh such as test Runner performance
toet and many others we use aoo for
GitHub which is another product that
Microsoft is developing as a backbone
for devops this is how we run the builds
and uh test the apps Etc and the last
thing I want to emphasize here is that
this is not the place to report product
defects with any customer impact there
are like other channels to do that so
please don't use the
repository now here you can see the rest
of the page that you're going to see
when you go to akms BC apps here in the
center you can see and browse the source
code and and um try to see how it's
organized on the right side uh there is
a link to the reference documentations
where you can read the reference
documentation for the code that is uh
right here on the main branch up in the
issue steps you can see what work is
being planned by the by the community
this is going to be uh some work that
the community wants to address in this
repository and pro possibly the most
important part is the P requests app
where you can go and see what is
currently being worked on actively
worked on this is where both Microsoft
developers and Community developers they
collaborate each other they Cod develop
uh you can go and browse put requests
leave comments we already receive
feedback that this this feedback is
actually quite valuable for our
developers and one thing you would
actually notice that I want to mention
here is that we run several automation
pool requests these are PO requests
taged with the automation tag and you
don't really need to do anything about
them you just I just want to briefly
cover them so that you're aware what
automations we actually run in the BC
apps Repository first and foremost um we
have an automation that updates the BC
artifact version in our aogo settings
this is because our po request builds
and cic builds they run against a
concrete BC artifact version that is
mainly due to the fact that we want to
rerun the same builds with the same
configurations and we don't we want to
ensure the development cycle is not
broken and the next two automations
combined is automation that updates the
app baselines version and the
translation package versions the former
you updates the package version for the
app baselines and we use these baselines
to compile the apps and to ensure no new
Breaking changes are introduced the the
second automation is to update the
translation package versions and we do
that mainly to ensure that translations
and apps are compatible now if you're
already curious how you can build your
own Pro request Alexander here is going
to walk you through the process thank
you Maria so I'll in this next session
of the presentation I'll talk about the
contribution process for you as a
contributor out there in the BC
Community I'll go through an end-to-end
process of how you can go from an idea
or a bug uh that you've discovered in
the product to uh to actually merging
your PO request and making it into the
product so to get started with contrib
contributing to the BCF processor the
first thing you'll need is just an idea
or a book um so an idea could be
something you find on the BC ideas page
um it could also be an idea that you've
subed yourself to the BCI IDs page uh or
you can find a bug in the product uh
ideally not something with customer
impact because as Mar already mentioned
that should something we should expedite
uh but if you have something that just
is mildly annoying to you and you want
to you have a way of fixing it by all
means um continue with a
contribution the second step in this
process is that you need to create an
issue on GitHub if you go under the
issues tab you should be able to see
these options and you want to select one
of the top two ones so either you want
to implement a BC idea or you want to
fix a book when you click get started it
will take you to a form they you need to
fill out it's just to give you some to
give us some information of what it is
you want to
do once you open up an issue this is
really the place where you can
collaborate with the BC community and
members of the Microsoft team in order
to figure out what it is you want to
implement maybe there are some
clarifying questions that need to be
asked um the thing to look out for is
here on the right side you'll get an
approve label and the approv label Bas
basically means that youve gotten the
go-ahead for Microsoft to continue with
this contribution we support you in the
contribution and we're looking forward
to seeing your pool request so once you
have the approved label then you can go
ahead and start with start developing
basically um and to start developing
probably the easiest way to do that is
just by creating a fork of the BC apps
repository on the GitHub page it's
relatively simple just click on the fork
icon and then you're
off the second step is to then set up
your Dev environment this is a bit up to
you how you set it up but we we've
documented how to do this with BC
container Helper and Docker uh we
essentially have a script that you can
run type in the right parameters and
you're off you have a local Docker
environment where you can publish your
apps to and you can test uh you can test
it manually you can write test cases run
those tests uh however you develop you
can do that in these
containers Next Step here as I mentioned
time to develop this is when you get to
develop your buck fix or your idea or
you know write the test
uh test it manually get a coworker to
test it with you however you normally uh
develop once you're happy with with what
you have then it's time to open up a
pool request now opening up a pool
request again is done through the GitHub
UI and all you need to provide is a
title a good description of what it is
that you're trying to do if you have
GitHub co-pilot this is very easy
because you can just get co-pilot to do
it for you and then the last step here
is to link your pull request to your
approved GitHub issue now the way you do
that is just by writing a hashtag and
then the number of your issue so if you
go under the issues uh page in GitHub it
should say a number like 123 so just
write # 1223 if that's your issue number
once you open up your poll request we
have some automation that starts kicking
off right away this is also when members
of the BC community and Engineers of
Microsoft will take a look at your PR
write some comments um you know ask some
questions about what it is you're doing
uh but if you scroll down to the bottom
of your PR you'll see
uh a summary that GitHub gives you now
in this summary in the top here this
section is really focused on the code
review aspect of what we require to
merge your PR so in this case here yeser
is requesting me to make some changes I
can see I I don't have quite the
approvals yet uh there's still some
comments I need to
resolve in the bottom part here that's
where we report the automated checks so
we have checks for checking for work
items and the polar request build and so
on so I think it's worthwhile to go
through each of the one of these one by
one to see what it is that's required to
merge a PR into the BC apps
repository so starting off with comments
the first thing we require is that all
comments are resolved as as I said when
you when you open up your poll request
you'll get comments from us in Microsoft
or other members of the BC community and
you know comments could be as simple as
just committing a suggestion or it could
be something like uh and a disc
discussion item that you need to resolve
with the reviewer the important thing
here is that all these conversations are
resolved before the pr can be merged the
Second Step here is that you need
approvals we require at least two
approvals from maintainers of the BCS
repository which essentially means two
approvals from U engineers at
Microsoft as for automated checks we
check for uh linked work items so as I
as I mentioned earlier it's important
when you open up your pool request that
you link to uh an approved issue and
that's because we have a check on the
poll request that looks for links to uh
issues and if you if you don't have a
link to an issue or if the issue that
you're linking to is not approved then
you'll get a comment in your PR
explaining what the next steps are
luckily it's very easy to resolve once
you have your approved issue you can
just write hashtag and then your issue
ID and the common goes away and this
check becomes
green the next check is called for
Microsoft validate link to internal work
items now there are no action items for
you here as a contributor this is a
reminder to us in Microsoft that there's
some internal accounting we need to do
for example if your change needs to be
reflected in uh the release notes then
this this is a reminder for us to do
that but there is no action for you as a
contributor the last and probably more
significant of these checks is the pull
request build now here we actually take
what you've built and we we try to
compile that and test that in our gates
and the requirement here is that
everything compiles all code Cup rules
satisfied and that tests are passing if
you open up a pus build it'll look a
little bit like this there's a lot going
on here uh many green checks here this
is an example of a successful one
unfortunately GitHub doesn't do a great
job at displaying this so I'll try to
represent it a bit of a different way in
that our proquest build essentially
consists of two phases a build phase and
a test phase in the build phase we build
the system application the business
Foundation the test framework and so on
uh all the apps essentially in the
Repository and we build those apps in
three different flavors we build it in
the vanilla mode which is just compiling
the app as it is then we build it with
translations as well and then we build
it in clean mode now clean mode means
that we apply these pre-processor
attacks that we use um our pre-processed
attacks are clean for example here we
have clean 23 and it just means that
this snippet of code here will not be
included in the clean build but would be
included in uh the other
builds there's just a bit of a
difference between the our different
build modes now mo more often than not
you'll see if one of them fails then all
of them fails but there are cases where
only the clean build would fail and the
normal vanilla build of the system
application would not so that's just
something to keep in mind in the second
phase we start testing and we we test
the system application and the business
Foundation both in the vanilla mode but
also in uh clean mode if everything goes
well everything compiles all tests pass
you'll see your poqu build looking like
this uh but that's not always the case
and sometimes uh things are
failing and to discuss what you need to
do when things are failing I'll go
through a short demo of of an example of
where something is failing and how you
can fix that so here I have a polar
Quest and just to explain the polar
Quest really quickly uh it just it
changes the headlines implementation uh
to just the first time a user logs in it
displays a different message so in this
case it displays welcome to business
Central the first time you log in now I
open up this pull request I provided a
summary and I linked to my
issue when I scroll down I can see that
some checks are not successful so I have
five failing checks so when I scroll
through the list I see this for
Microsoft check that's failing as I
mentioned there's no action item for you
so just feel free to ignore it but if I
scroll further down I see that building
the system application fails and it
fails both in default clean and
translated mode so now I know that
there's something I need to do uh now
because it fail fails in the build phase
one trick that you can use is just to go
up to the files uh tab
here and not only can you see my changes
but GitHub actually also reports uh what
the compilation issues are so in this
case it says here that I haven't given
an argument that requires that
corresponds to the required formal
parameter use a security ID in is first
login so here I'm calling a function
called is first login but I didn't give
any guit as an input and I was supposed
to do that uh so I made a mistake here
and that caused a compilation issue so
that's an example of how you can debug a
compilation issue in your PR now to fix
that you can either do it in vs code or
you can go up here and click edit file
however you prefer to do
it now let's say I fixed that so I have
another PR here where I fixed that
compilation issue I go under files
changed
and under files changed I see that I now
pass an input to this function uh that
is of gu type and now GitHub is not
complaining about any compilation issues
anymore so if I scroll back up again and
I go back out into the conversation tab
scroll down I still see I still have
four failing checks so if I scroll
through the list I see building the
system application in default clean and
translated mode that now succeeds but
when I scroll past that I see that
building this system application tests
is failing so let's take a deeper look
at that if we go under the details
tab uh there are two ways you can kind
of figure out what's going wrong here
but probably the easiest way is to go
under
summary and when you scroll through the
summary you see it a couple places here
for example we can see we have some test
function here that failed it expected
one message but got another um if you
scroll past that and all the way down to
the bottom algo actually provides a nice
summary of all the tests that we're
running and which ones are failing so
here for example the business Foundation
tests are all succeeding that's great
but when you scroll past that we see
that the system application tests uh are
mostly succeeding but one of them failed
uh so the way you can debug that and
figure out what's going on is just to
expand this section here and now we can
see that it's it's a headline test that
failed is this particular test case
called test get user greeting and we can
also see the stack Trace so this is when
you as a as a developer can can use that
information to then either fix your test
or fix the
implementation uh once you fix that
hopefully the checks become green and
and once you get the approvals we're
ready to
merge so to wrap up I've made a short
checklist of what it takes to make a
contribution into the BC apps repository
first of all you need that all Commons
are resolved you need at least two
approvers you need to link your polar to
an issue and then the poest build needs
to be passing meaning no compilation
issues and no test failures if you can
check out all these boxes then you can
merge your
pquest and you've made a contribution
into the bcfs repository if for whatever
reason you can check off most of the
boxes but one of them for some reason
you can't let's say the pulus build is
failing and you just can't figure out
why or you think that you've linked your
issue but for some reason it just GitHub
doesn't recognize that you've linked
your issue by all means just ask for
help in your PO request create a comment
in the pull request and a member
of our team or someone in the BC
Community will help you out uh as we
mentioned earlier BC apps is truly a
community effort and so there are people
looking at this repository every day uh
and at least our engineers in Microsoft
are very familiar with the process of
getting a contribution into the BCF
repository so there'll be there'll be
people out there to to help you
out if you discover a buck in the
contribution process meaning you can't
spin up a container for some reason or
you find that our documentation is
lacking or is missing some information
by all means create an issue for us we
have an issue template for that it's
called report a bug in the contribution
process and we'll take a look as quickly
as possible we want to smoothen out the
contribution process as much as we can
so please help us out if you find a bug
in the contribution
process thank you Alex for this lovely
demonstration of the contribution
process now I've prepared we've prepared
uh several key takeaways from these
sessions and first and foremost is that
c development is Microsoft visions of
business Central application if you
haven't gotten the memo yet this is
indeed why we're doing uh all the GitHub
work we do this is why we are moving to
True open source this is why we're
moving our internal development to
GitHub so this is the place where
Microsoft developers can indeed
co-develop with all the partners we have
out there for business Central next I
also want to emphasize that contribution
is the same for everyone uh all the
checks that Alex mentioned earlier
they are the same for both internal
developers and for everyone else out
there we require the same number of
recurs the same number of reviewers the
same checks need to pass on every po
request no matter if it's external or
internal and again as Alexander
mentioned do not hesitate to ask we
would hate to see you get stuck on
something that is uh might be like an
issue on our side or might some
sometimes it just might be like a
instability or whatever just ask us for
help so if you're eager to start just go
to akms BC apps and explore our
repository here we have compiled a list
of other resources that you can check
out in order to connect with other
members of the community or have more
documentation on your s when you are
trying to contribute to BC apps next I
want to promote a session from our
colleagues uh that is about business
foundation and the number series modules
and I want to emphasize that business
Foundation was indeed the first
applications application that uh was
developed on GitHub from the beginning
so please check out the sessions to
familiarize yourself more about this
application with that I want to say
thank you and see you on
GitHub